<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4918 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4918.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5545 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5545.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7986 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8288 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8288.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8607 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8607.xml">
<!ENTITY W3C.REC-skos-reference-20090818 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-w3c/reference.W3C.REC-skos-reference-20090818.xml">
<!ENTITY W3C.WD-xptr-xpointer-20021219 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.WD-xptr-xpointer-20021219.xml">
<!ENTITY W3C.REC-xptr-framework-20030325 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xptr-framework-20030325.xml">
        ]>

<rfc category="std"
     updates='5545' 
     docName="draft-ietf-calext-ical-relations-09" ipr="trust200902">
        <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
        <?rfc toc="yes"?>
        <?rfc tocdepth="5"?>
        <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
        <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
        <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
        <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="iCalendar Relationships">Support for iCalendar Relationships</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <author initials="M." surname="Douglass" fullname="Michael Douglass">
      <organization abbrev="Bedework">Bedework</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>226 3rd Street</street>
          <city>Troy</city>
          <region>NY</region>
          <code>12180</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mdouglass@bedework.com</email>
        <uri>http://bedework.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day='23' month='January' year='2022' />

    <area>Applications</area>

    <keyword>iCalendar</keyword>

    <keyword>link</keyword>
    <keyword>related-to</keyword>
    <keyword>relationships</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This specification updates the iCalendar RELATED-TO property
        by adding new relation types and introduces new iCalendar
        properties LINK, CONCEPT and REFID to allow better
        linking and grouping of iCalendar components and related data.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        iCalendar entities defined in <xref target='RFC5545'/> often
        need to be related to each other or to
        associated meta-data. The specifications below support
        relationships of the following forms:
        <list style='hanging'>
          <t hangText="Structured iCalendar:">
            iCalendar entities can be related to each other in some structured
            way, for example as parent, sibling, before, after.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Grouped iCalendar:">
            iCalendar entities can be related to each other as a group.
            CATEGORIES are often used for this purpose but are problematic
            for application developers due to their lack of consistency
            and use as a free-form tag.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Linked:">
            Entities can be linked to other entities such as vcards
            through a URI and associated REL and FMTTYPE parameters.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <section title="Structured iCalendar relationships">
        <t>
          The iCalendar <xref target='RFC5545'/>
          RELATED-TO property has no support for temporal relationships
          as used by standard project management tools.
        </t>

        <t>
          The RELTYPE parameter is extended to take new values
          defining temporal relationships, a GAP parameter is defined to provide
          lead and lag values, and RELATED-TO is extended to allow URI values.
          These changes allow the RELATED-TO property to define a richer set of
          relationships useful for project management.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Grouped iCalendar relationships">
        <t>
          This specification defines a new REFID property which
          allows arbitrary groups of entities to be associated with the same
          key value. 
        </t>
        
        <t>
          REFID is used to identify a key allowing the association of components
          that are related to the same object and retrieval of a component based on
          this key. Two examples of how this may be used are to identify the tasks
          associated with a given project without having to communicate the
          task structure of the project, and to group all tasks associated to
          a specific package in a package delivery system.
        </t>

        <t>
          As such, the presence of a REFID property imparts no meaning
          to the component. It is merely a key to allow retrieval. This is
          distinct from categorisation which, while allowing grouping
          also adds meaning to the component to which it is attached.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Concept relationships">
        <t>
          The name CONCEPT is used by the Simple Knowledge Organization
          System defined in <xref target='W3C.REC-skos-reference-20090818'/>.
          The term "concept" more accurately defines what we often
          mean by a category. It's not the text string that is important
          but the meaning attached to it. For example, the term
          "football" can mean very different sports.
        </t>

        <t>
          The introduction of CONCEPT allows a more structured
          approach to categorization, with the possibility of namespaced
          and path-like values. Unlike REFID the CONCEPT property imparts some
          meaning. It is assumed that the value of this property will
          reference a well defined category.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          The current <xref target='RFC5545'/> CATEGORY property is used
          as a free form 'tagging' field. As such it is difficult to establish
          formal relationships between components based on their category.
        </t>

        <t>
          Rather than attempt to add semantics to the CATEGORY property
          it seems best to continue its usage as an informal tag and
          establish a new CONCEPT property with more constraints.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Linked relationships">
        <t>
          The currently existing iCalendar standard <xref target='RFC5545'/> lacks
          a general purpose method for referencing additional, external information
          relating to calendar components.
        </t>

        <t>
          This document proposes a method for referencing typed external
          information that can provide additional information about an iCalendar
          component. This new LINK property is closely aligned to the LINK header
          defined in
          <xref target='RFC8288'/>
        </t>

        <t>
          The LINK property defines a typed reference or relation to external
          meta-data or related resources. By providing type and format information
          as parameters, clients and servers are able to discover interesting
          references and make use of them, perhaps for indexing or the
          presentation of interesting links for the user.
        </t>

        <t>
          It is also often necessary to reference calendar components
          in other collections. For example, a VEVENT might refer to
          a VTODO from which it was derived. The PARENT, SIBLING and CHILD
          relationships defined for the
          RELATED-TO property only allow for a UID which is inadequate for many
          purposes. Allowing other value types for those relationships may help
          but would cause
          backward compatibility issues. The LINK property can link components
          in different collections or even on different servers.
        </t>

        <t>
          When publishing events it is useful to be able to refer back to the
          source of that information. The actual event may have been consumed from
          a feed or an ics file on a web site. A LINK property can provide
          a reference to the originator of the event.
        </t>

        <t>
          Beyond the need to relate elements temporally, project
          management tools often need to be able to specify the relationships
          between the various events and tasks which make up a project.
          The LINK property provides such a mechanism.
        </t>

        <t>
          The LINK property MUST NOT be treated as just another
          attachment. The ATTACH property defined in
          <xref target='RFC5545'/> is being extended to handle
          server-side management and stripping of inline data. Clients
          may choose to handle attachments differently from the LINK
          property as they are often
          an integral part of the message - for example, the agenda.
        </t>

        <t>
          For more information on managed attachments see
          <xref target='RFC8607'/>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="caching" title='Caching and offline use'>
        <t>
          To facilitate offline display the link type may identify
          important pieces of data which should be downloaded in
          advance.
        </t>
        <t>
          In general, the calendar entity should be self explanatory
          without the need to download referenced meta-data such as a
          web page.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="conventions"
               title='Conventions Used in This Document'>
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
          "MAY" and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in BCP 14 <xref target='RFC2119'/>
          <xref target='RFC8174'/> when, and only when, they
          appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="reference_types"
             title="Reference Types">
      <t>
        The actual reference value can take three forms specified by the type
        parameter
        <list style='hanging'>
          <t hangText="URI:">
            The default type. This is a URI referring to the target.
          </t>
          <t hangText="UID:">
            This allows for linking within a single collection and the value
            MUST be another component within that collection.
          </t>
          <t hangText="REFERENCE:">
            In an XML environment it may be necessary to refer to a
            fragment of an external XML artifact. This value is a URI
            with an XPointer anchor value. The XPointer is defined in
            <xref target='W3C.WD-xptr-xpointer-20021219'/> and it's
            use as an anchor is defined in <xref target="W3C.REC-xptr-framework-20030325"/>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="link_relation_types"
             title="Link Relation Types">
      <t>
        <xref target='RFC8288'/> defines two forms of relation type: registered and
        extension.  Registered relation types are added to the Link
        Relations registry as specified in Section 2.1.1 of <xref target='RFC8288'/>.
        Extension relation types, defined in Section 2.1.2 of <xref target='RFC8288'/>,
        are specified as unique URIs that are not registered in the registry.
      </t>

      <t>
        The relation types defined in <xref target="linkrel" /> will
        be registered with IANA in
        accordance with the specifications in  <xref target='RFC8288'/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="new_temporal_reltype_values"
             title="New temporal RELTYPE Parameter values">
      <t>
        This section defines the usual temporal relationships
        for use with the RELTYPE parameter defined in
        Section 3.2.15 of <xref target='RFC5545' />:
        FINISHTOSTART, FINISHTOFINISH, STARTTOFINISH or STARTTOSTART.
      </t>

      <t>
        The <xref target='RFC5545'/> RELATED-TO property with one or
        more of these temporal relationships will be present in the
        predecessor entity and will refer to the successor entity.
      </t>

      <t>
        The GAP parameter (see <xref target='gap'/>)
        specifies the lead or lag time between the predecessor and
        the successor. In the description of each temporal relationship
        below we refer to Task-A, which contains and controls the relationship, and
        Task-B the target of the relationship.
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="RELTYPE=FINISHTOSTART:">
            Task-B cannot start until Task-A finishes.
            For example, when sanding is complete, painting can begin.
            <figure anchor='finishtostart' title='Finish to start relationship'>
              <artwork><![CDATA[

            ============
            |  Task-A  |--+
            ============  |
                          |
                          V
                          ============
                          |  Task-B  |
                          ============
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t hangText="RELTYPE=FINISHTOFINISH:">
            Task-B can only be completed after Task-A
            is finished. The related tasks may run in parallel before
            completion.
          </t>
          <t>
            For example, if the goal is to prepare a meal, we start the
            potatoes, then the meat then the peas
            but they should all be cooked at the same time.
            <figure anchor='finishtofinish' title='Finish to finish relationship'>
              <artwork><![CDATA[

                    ==================
                    |     Task-A     |--+
                    ==================  |
                                        |
                          ============  |
                          |  Task-B  |<-+
                          ============
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t hangText="RELTYPE=STARTTOFINISH:">
            The start of Task-A (which occurs after Task-B)
            controls the finish of Task-B.
            For example, ticket sales (Task-B) end when the game
            starts (Task-A).
            <figure anchor='starttofinish' title='Start to finish relationship'>
              <artwork><![CDATA[

                                     ============
                                  +--|  Task-A  |
                                  |  ============
                                  |
                    ============  |
                    |  Task-B  |<-+
                    ============
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t hangText="RELTYPE=STARTTOSTART:">
            The start of Task-A triggers the start of Task-B,
            that is Task-B can start anytime after Task-A starts.
            <figure anchor='starttostart' title='Start to start relationship'>
              <artwork><![CDATA[

                    ============
                 +--|  Task-A  |
                 |  ============
                 |
                 |  ============
                 +->|  Task-B  |
                    ============
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="additional_new_reltype_values"
             title="Additional New RELTYPE Parameter Values">
      <t>
        This section defines the additional relationships below:
      </t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="RELTYPE=FIRST:">
            Indicates that the referenced calendar component is the
            first in a series the referenced calendar component is
            part of.
          </t>

          <t hangText="RELTYPE=DEPENDS-ON:">
            Indicates that the current calendar component depends on
            the referenced calendar component in some manner. For example
            a task may be blocked waiting on the other, referenced, task.
          </t>

          <t hangText="RELTYPE=REFID:">
            Establishes a reference from the current component to
            components with a REFID property which matches the value
            given in the associated RELATED-TO property.
          </t>

          <t hangText="RELTYPE=CONCEPT:">
            Establishes a reference from the current component to
            components with a CONCEPT property which matches the value
            given in the associated RELATED-TO property.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="new_property_parameters"
             title="New Property Parameters">
      <section anchor="linkrel"
               title="Link Relation">
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="Parameter name:">
              LINKREL
            </t>

            <t hangText="Purpose:">
              To specify the relationship of data referenced by a LINK property.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Format Definition:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  This parameter is defined by the following notation:
                </preamble>

                <artwork type="abnf">
  linkrelparam = "LINKREL" "="
                 ("SOURCE"      ; Link to source of this component
                 / DQUOTE uri DQUOTE
                 / iana-token)   ; Other IANA registered type
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Description:">
              This parameter MUST be specified on all LINK properties, and
              defines the type of reference. This allows programs consuming this
              data to automatically scan for references they support. There is no default relation type.
            </t>

            <t>
              In addition to the values defined here any value defined
              in <xref target='RFC8288'/> may be used. However these uses
              SHOULD be documented in an RFC updating both
              <xref target='RFC5545'/> and <xref target='RFC8288'/>
            </t>

            <t hangText="LINKREL=SOURCE:">
              identifies the source of the event information.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Registration:">
              These relation types are registered in <xref target='RFC8288'/>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="gap" title="Gap">
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="Parameter name:">
              GAP
            </t>

            <t hangText="Purpose:">
              To specify the length of the gap, positive or negative,
              between two temporaly related components.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Format Definition:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  This parameter is defined by the following notation:
                </preamble>

                <artwork type="abnf">
  gapparam      = "GAP" "=" dur-value
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Description:">
              This parameter MAY be specified on the RELATED-TO property, and
              defines the duration of time between the predecessor and successor
              in an interval. When positive it defines the lag time between
              a task and its logical successor. When negative it defines
              the lead time.
            </t>

            <t>
              An example of lag time might be if task A is "paint the room"
              and task B is
              "hang the drapes" then task A may be related to task B with
              RELTYPE=FINISHTOSTART with a gap long enough for the paint to
              dry.
            </t>

            <t>
              An example of lead time might be to relate a 1 week task A
              to the end of task B with RELTYPE=STARTTOFINISH and a
              negative gap of 1 week so they finish at the same time.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="new_value_data_types"
             title="New Value Data Types">
      <t>
        This specification defines the following new value types to
        be used with the VALUE property parameter:

        <list style='hanging'>
          <t hangText="UID">
            VALUE=UID indicates that the associated value is the UID for a
            component.
          </t>

          <t hangText="REFERENCE">
            VALUE=REFERENCE indicates that the associated value
            references an associated XML artifact and is a URI
            with an XPointer anchor value. The XPointer is defined in
            <xref target='W3C.WD-xptr-xpointer-20021219'/> and it's
            use as an anchor is defined in <xref target="W3C.REC-xptr-framework-20030325"/>.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="new_properties"
             title="New Properties">
      <section anchor="concept"
               title="Concept">
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="Property name:">
              CONCEPT
            </t>

            <t hangText="Purpose:">
              This property defines the formal categories for a calendar
              component. 
            </t>

            <t hangText="Value type:">
              URI
            </t>

            <t hangText="Property Parameters:">
              IANA, and non-standard parameters can be specified on this property.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Conformance:">
              This property can be specified zero or more times in any
              iCalendar component.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Description:">
              This property is used to specify formal categories or
              classifications of the calendar component.  The values
              are useful in searching for a calendar component of a
              particular type and category.
            </t>

            <t>
              Within the "VEVENT", "VTODO", or "VJOURNAL" calendar components,
              more than one formal category can be specified by using multiple
              CONCEPT properties.
            </t>

            <t>
              This categorization is distinct from the more informal
              "tagging" of components provided by the existing CATEGORIES
              property. It is expected that the value of the CONCEPT
              property will reference an external resource which
              provides information about the categorization.
            </t>

            <t>
              In addition, a structured URI value allows for
              hierarchical categorization of events.
            </t>

            <t>
              Possible category resources are the various proprietary
              systems, for example Library of Congress, or an open
              source of categorisation data.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Format Definition:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  This property is defined by the following notation:
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
  concept        =  "CONCEPT" conceptparam ":"
                        uri CRLF

  conceptparam = *(";" other-param)

                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Example:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  The following is an example of this property. It points to a
                  server acting as the source for the calendar object.
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
  CONCEPT:http://example.com/event-types/arts/music
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="link"
               title="Link">
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="Property name:">
              LINK
            </t>

            <t hangText="Purpose:">
              This property provides a reference to external information
              related to a component.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Value type:">
              URI, TEXT or REFERENCE
            </t>

            <t hangText="Property Parameters:">
              The VALUE parameter is required.
              Non-standard, reference type or format type parameters can also be
              specified on this property. The LABEL parameter
              is defined in <xref target='RFC7986'/>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Conformance:">
              This property can be specified zero or more times in any
              iCalendar component.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Description:">
              When used in a component the value of this property points to
              additional information related to the component. For example,
              it may reference the originating web server.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Format Definition:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  This property is defined by the following notation:
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
   link           = "LINK" linkparam ":"
                      ( uri /  ; for VALUE=REFERENCE
                        uri /  ; for VALUE=URI
                        text ) ; for VALUE=TEXT
                    CRLF

   linkparam      = ; the elements herein may appear in any order,
                    ; and the order is not significant.

                    (";" "VALUE" "=" ("REFERENCE" /
                                      "URI" /
                                      "TEXT"))
                    1*(";" linkrelparam)
                    (";" fmttypeparam)
                    (";" labelparam)
                    (";" langparam)
                    *(";" other-param)

                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t>
              This property is a serialisation of the model in
              <xref target="RFC8288"/>, where the link target is
              carried in the property value, the link context is the
              containing calendar entity, and the link relation type
              and any target attributes are carried in iCalendar property
              parameters.
            </t>

            <t>
              The LINK property parameters
              map to <xref target="RFC8288"/> attributes as follows:

              <list style='hanging'>
                <t hangText="LABEL:">
                  Maps to the "title" attribute defined in section 3.4.1 of <xref target="RFC8288"/>.
                </t>
                <t hangText="LANG:">
                  Maps to the "hreflang" attribute defined in section 3.4.1 of <xref target="RFC8288"/>.
                </t>
                <t hangText="LINKREL:">
                  Maps to the link relation type defined in section 2.1 of <xref target="RFC8288"/>.
                </t>
                <t hangText="FMTTYPE:">
                  Maps to the "type" attribute defined in section 3.4.1 of <xref target="RFC8288"/>.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t>
              There is no mapping for <xref target="RFC8288"/> "title*",
              "anchor", "rev" or "media".
            </t>

            <t hangText="Example:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  The following is an example of this property which
                  provides a reference to the source for the calendar object.
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
  LINK;LINKREL=SOURCE;LABEL=Venue;VALUE=URI:http://example.com/events
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Example:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  The following is an example of this property which
                  provides a reference to an entity from which this one
                  was derived. The link relation is a vendor defined value
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
  LINK;LINKREL="https://example.com/linkrel/derivedFrom";VALUE=URI:
   http://example.com/tasks/01234567-abcd1234.ics
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Example:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  The following is an example of this property which
                  provides a reference to a fragment of an XML document.
                  The link relation is a vendor defined value
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
  LINK;LINKREL="https://example.com/linkrel/costStructure";
   VALUE=REFERENCE:
   http://example.com/xmlDocs/bidFramework.xml
   #xpointer(descendant::CostStruc/range-to(following::CostStrucEND[1]))
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="refid"
               title="Refid">
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="Property name:">
              REFID
            </t>

            <t hangText="Purpose:">
              This property value acts as a key for associated
              iCalendar entities.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Value type:">
              TEXT
            </t>

            <t hangText="Property Parameters:">
              Non-standard parameters can be specified on this property.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Conformance:">
              This property can be specified zero or more times in any
              iCalendar component.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Description:">
              The value of this property is free-form text that
              creates an identifier for associated components.  All components
              that use the same REFID value are associated through that value
              and can be located or retrieved as a group.  For example, all of
              the events in a travel itinerary would have the same REFID value,
              so as to be grouped together.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Format Definition:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  This property is defined by the following notation:
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
  refid      = "REFID" refidparam ":" text CRLF


  refidparam      = *(";" other-param)

                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t>
              The current link registry
            </t>

            <t hangText="Example:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  The following is an example of this property.
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
  REFID:itinerary-2014-11-17
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="updates_to_rfc_5545"
             title="Updates to RFC 5545">
      <t>
        This specification updates the RELATED-TO property defined
        in Section 3.8.4.5 of <xref target='RFC5545'/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        The RELTYPE parameter is extended to take new values defining
        temporal relationships, a GAP parameter is defined to provide lead
        and lag values, and RELATED-TO is extended to allow URI values.
        These changes allow the RELATED-TO property to define a richer set of
        relationships useful for project management.
      </t>

      <section anchor="related-to"
               title="RELATED-TO">
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="Property name:">
              RELATED-TO
            </t>

            <t hangText="Purpose:">
              This property is used to represent a relationship or
              reference between one calendar component and another. The definition
              here extends the definition in Section 3.8.4.5 of
              <xref target='RFC5545'/> by allowing URI or UID values and a GAP parameter.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Value type:">
              URI, UID or TEXT
            </t>

            <t hangText="Property Parameters:">
              Relationship type, IANA and non-standard
              property parameters can be specified on this property.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Conformance:">
              This property MAY be specified in any iCalendar component.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Description:">
              By default or when VALUE=UID is specified, the property value
              consists of the persistent, globally
              unique identifier of another calendar component.  This value would
              be represented in a calendar component by the "UID" property.
            </t>

            <t>
              By default, the property value points to another calendar
              component that has a PARENT relationship to the referencing
              object.  The "RELTYPE" property parameter is used to either
              explicitly state the default PARENT relationship type to the
              referenced calendar component or to override the default PARENT
              relationship type and specify either a CHILD or SIBLING
              relationship or a temporal relationship.
            </t>

            <t>
              The PARENT relationship indicates that the calendar
              component is a subordinate of the referenced calendar component.
              The CHILD relationship indicates that the calendar component is a
              superior of the referenced calendar component.  The SIBLING
              relationship indicates that the calendar component is a peer of
              the referenced calendar component.
            </t>

            <t>
              To preserve backwards compatibility the value type MUST
              be UID when the PARENT, SIBLING or CHILD
              relationships are specified.
            </t>

            <t>
              The FINISHTOSTART, FINISHTOFINISH, STARTTOFINISH or STARTTOSTART
              relationships define temporal relationships as specified in the
              reltype parameter definition.
            </t>

            <t>
              Changes to a calendar component referenced by this property can
              have an implicit impact on the related calendar component.  For
              example, if a group event changes its start or end date or time,
              then the related, dependent events will need to have their start
              and end dates changed in a corresponding way.  Similarly, if a
              PARENT calendar component is cancelled or deleted, then there is
              an implied impact to the related CHILD calendar components.  This
              property is intended only to provide information on the
              relationship of calendar components.  It is up to the target
              calendar system to maintain any property implications of this
              relationship.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Format Definition:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  This property is defined by the following notation:
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
   related    = "RELATED-TO" relparam ":"
                            ( uid /  ; for VALUE=UID
                              uri /  ; for VALUE=URI
                              text ) ; for VALUE=TEXT or default
                CRLF

   relparam   = ; the elements herein may appear in any order,
                ; and the order is not significant.
                [";" "VALUE" "=" ("UID" /
                                  "URI" /
                                  "TEXT")]
                [";" reltypeparam]
                [";" gapparam]
                *(";" other-param)
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Example:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  The following are examples of this property.
                </preamble>

                <artwork>
  RELATED-TO:jsmith.part7.19960817T083000.xyzMail@example.com

  RELATED-TO:19960401-080045-4000F192713-0052@example.com

  RELATED-TO;VALUE=URI;RELTYPE=STARTTOFINISH:
   http://example.com/caldav/user/jb/cal/
   19960401-080045-4000F192713.ics
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title='Security Considerations'>
      <t>
       Applications using the LINK property need to be aware of the risks
       entailed in using the URIs provided as values. See section 7 of
        <xref target='RFC3986'/> for
       a discussion of the security considerations relating to URIs.
      </t>

      <t>
        In particular note section 7.1 "Reliability and Consistency" of
        <xref target='RFC3986'/> which points out the lack of a stability
        guarantee for referenced resources.
      </t>

      <t>
        When the value is a REFERENCE type the targeted data is an XML document
        or portion thereof. Consumers need to be aware of the security issues
        related to XML processing - in particular those related to XML entities.
        See <xref target='RFC4918'/> - Section 20.6. Additionally note that
        the reference may be invalid or become so over time.
      </t>
      <t>
        The CONCEPT and redefined RELATED-TO property have
        the same issues in that values may be URIs.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana_considerations" title='IANA Considerations'>
      <section anchor="property_registrations"
               title="iCalendar Property Registrations" >
        <t>
          The following iCalendar property names have been added to
          the iCalendar Properties Registry defined in Section 8.3.2 of
          <xref target='RFC5545'/>  IANA has also added a
          reference to this document where the properties originally defined in
          <xref target='RFC5545'/> have been updated by this document.
        </t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

          <c>CONCEPT</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="concept"/></c>

          <c>LINK</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="link"/></c>

          <c>REFID</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="refid"/></c>

          <c>RELATED-TO</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target='RFC5545'/>, <xref target="related-to"/></c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section anchor="property_parameter_registrations"
               title="iCalendar Property Parameter Registrations" >
        <t>
          The following iCalendar property parameter names have been added to
          the iCalendar Parameters Registry defined in Section 8.3.3 of
          <xref target='RFC5545'/>
        </t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left">Parameter</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

          <c>GAP</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="gap"/></c>

          <c>LINKREL</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="linkrel"/></c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section anchor="value_data_types_registrations"
               title="iCalendar Value Data Type Registrations" >
        <t>
          The following iCalendar property parameter names have been added to
          the iCalendar Value Data Types Registry defined in Section 8.3.4 of
          <xref target='RFC5545'/>
        </t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left">Value Data Type</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

          <c>REFERENCE</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="new_value_data_types"/></c>

          <c>UID</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="new_value_data_types"/></c>
        </texttable>
      </section>


      <section anchor="reltype_value_registrations"
               title="iCalendar RELTYPE Value Registrations" >
        <t>
          The following iCalendar "RELTYPE" values have been added to
          the iCalendar Relationship Types Registry defined in Section 8.3.8 of
          <xref target='RFC5545'/>
        </t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left">Relationship Type</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

          <c>CONCEPT</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="additional_new_reltype_values"/></c>

          <c>DEPENDS-ON</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="additional_new_reltype_values"/></c>

          <c>FINISHTOFINISH</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="new_temporal_reltype_values"/></c>

          <c>FINISHTOSTART</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="new_temporal_reltype_values"/></c>

          <c>FIRST</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="additional_new_reltype_values"/></c>

          <c>REFID</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="additional_new_reltype_values"/></c>

          <c>STARTTOFINISH</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="new_temporal_reltype_values"/></c>

          <c>STARTTOSTART</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="new_temporal_reltype_values"/></c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section anchor="new_linkrel_registration"
               title="New Reference Type Registration">
        <t>
          The following link relation values have been added to
          the Reference Types Registry defined in Section 6.2.2 of
          <xref target='RFC8288'/>
        </t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

          <c>SOURCE</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c><xref target="linkrel"/></c>
        </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        The author would like to thank the members of the Calendaring and
        Scheduling Consortium technical committees and the following
        individuals for contributing their ideas, support and comments:
      </t>
      <t>
        Adrian Apthorp, Cyrus Daboo, Marten Gajda, Ken Murchison
      </t>
      <t>
        The author would also like to thank CalConnect, the Calendaring and
        Scheduling Consortium for advice with this specification.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC8607;
    </references>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC3986;
      &RFC4918;
      &RFC5545;
      &RFC7986;
      &RFC8174;
      &RFC8288;
      &W3C.WD-xptr-xpointer-20021219;
      &W3C.REC-xptr-framework-20030325;
      &W3C.REC-skos-reference-20090818;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
