<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-calext-jscalendar-icalendar-00">
    <?rfc toc="yes"?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
    <?rfc compact="no"?>
    <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
    <?rfc private=""?>
    <?rfc topblock="yes"?>
    <?rfc comments="no"?>

    <front>
        <title abbrev="JSCalendar">JSCalendar: Converting from and to iCalendar</title>
        <author initials="N.M." surname="Jenkins" fullname="Neil Jenkins">
            <organization>FastMail</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>PO Box 234</street>
                    <street>Collins St West</street>
                    <city>Melbourne</city>
                    <code>VIC 8007</code>
                    <country>Australia</country>
                    <region/>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <email>neilj@fastmailteam.com</email>
                <uri>https://www.fastmail.com</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="R." surname="Stepanek" fullname="Robert Stepanek">
            <organization>FastMail</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>PO Box 234</street>
                    <street>Collins St West</street>
                    <city>Melbourne</city>
                    <code>VIC 8007</code>
                    <country>Australia</country>
                    <region/>
                </postal>
                <email>rsto@fastmailteam.com</email>
                <uri>https://www.fastmail.com</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date year="2019" month="April" day="10"/>
        <area>Applications</area>
        <workgroup>Calendaring extensions</workgroup>
        <keyword>JSON</keyword>
        <keyword>iCalendar</keyword>
        <keyword>calendar</keyword>
        <keyword>events</keyword>
        <keyword>date</keyword>
        <keyword>time</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document defines a new set of properties for JSCalendar data and
                an informational guide for converting from and to iCalendar.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

            <section anchor="motivation" title="Motivation">
                <t>
                    The JSCalendar <xref target="draft-ietf-calext-jscalendar"/> data format
                    is used to represent calendar data, and is meant as an alternative to
                    the widely deployed iCalendar <xref target="RFC5545"/> data format.
                </t>
                <t>
                    While new calendaring services and applications might use JSCalendar
                    as their primary data format to exchange calendaring data, they will
                    have to interoperate with services and clients that just support iCalendar.
                    Similarly, existing calendaring data is stored in iCalendar format
                    in databases and other calendar stores, and providers and users might
                    want to represent this data also in JSCalendar. Lastly, some implementations
                    might want to preserve custom iCalendar properties, that have no
                    equivalent in JSCalendar when converting between these formats.
                </t>
                <t>
                    To facilitate these use cases, this document specifies new
                    properties in JSCalendar objects and tpes. It also defines an
                    informational guideline how to convert JSCalendar data from and to
                    iCalendar.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="scope" title="Scope and assumptions">
                <t>
                    This document defines how to embed iCalendar data
                    in JSCalendar and specifies the allowed value format and
                    contents. However, this document deliberately does not define a
                    canonical translation between these two formats, as this
                    might overly restrict implementations how to handle conversion.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Consequently, implementations MUST NOT make any
                    assumptions if and how this iCalendar data is processed.
                    Specifically, they MUST NOT expect either iCalendar or JSCalendar
                    data to have precendence in conflict, or how implementations
                    might convert between JSCalendar and iCalendar.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="new-jscalendar-props" title="New JSCalendar properties">
            <t>
                This section defines a new property for use in JSCalendar objects.
            </t>
            <section anchor="icalendar-properties" title="icalendarProperties">
                <t>
                    Type:
                    <spanx style="verb">String</spanx> (optional)
                </t>
                <t>
                    Defines additional properties of an instance of a JSCalendar object
                    with iCalendar semantics. The value MUST contain
                    valid jCal <xref target="RFC7265"/> formatted data. Depending on
                    the JSCalendar object or type, only a subset of iCalendar properties
                    might be permitted (see <xref target="mod-jscalendar-objects"/>).
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="mod-jscalendar-objects" title="Modifications to JCalendar objects and types">
            <t>
                This section defines all allowed occurrences of the
                <spanx style="emph">iCalendarProperties</spanx> property in
                JSCalendar types, or their related <spanx style="emph">PatchObject</spanx>
                in a <spanx style="emph">recurrenceOverride</spanx>.
                All other standard JSCalendar types MUST NOT contain iCalendar properties.
            </t>
            <t>
                In the following table, the first column names the JSCalendar type.
                The second column of the table defines the allowed iCalendar properties
                in the <spanx style="emph">iCalendarProperties</spanx> property
                of this type.
            </t>
            <texttable anchor="allowed-icalendar-props" title="Allowed occurrences of iCalendarProperties">

                <ttcol align='left'>JSCalendar type</ttcol>
                <ttcol align='left'>Allowed iCalendar data</ttcol>

                <c>JSGroup</c>
                <c>
                    All VCALENDAR component properties.
                </c>

                <c>JSEvent</c>
                <c>
                    All VEVENT component properties.
                </c>

                <c>JSTask</c>
                <c>
                    All VTODO component properties.
                </c>

                <c>Alert</c>
                <c>
                    All VALARM component properties.
                </c>
            </texttable>
            <t>
                Note that the iCalendar properties are not required to form a valid
                iCalendar component. For example, the iCalendar properties
                of a JSEvent may only contain a few iCalendar extension properties, and
                not any of the properties that are required for a valid VEVENT.
                However, an iCalendar property that isn't allowed for VEVENT also MUST
                NOT occur in the iCalendar properties of a JSEvent.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="icalendar-translation" title="Converting from and to iCalendar">
            <t>
                This section contains recommendations how to map JSCalendar from and to iCalendar.
            </t>
            <section anchor="translate-jsevent" title="JSEvent">
                <t>
                    The iCalendar counterpart to <spanx style="emph">JSEvent</spanx> is the VEVENT component type
                    <xref target="RFC5545"/>. A VEVENT component that is a direct child of a VCALENDAR component is
                    equivalent to a standalone JSEvent. A VEVENT component within a VEVENT
                    maps to the entries of
                    the JSEvent <spanx style="emph">recurrenceOverrides</spanx> property.
                </t>


                <texttable anchor="translate-jsevent-table" title="Translation between JSEvent and iCalendar">
                    <ttcol align='left'>Property</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='left'>iCalendar counterpart</ttcol>

                    <c>isAllDay</c>
                    <c>
                        True, if the type of the DTSTART property in iCalendar is DATE.
                    </c>

                    <c>start</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the DTSTART property in iCalendar. Note that time zone information is stored separately in JSEvent.
                    </c>

                    <c>timeZone</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the TZID part of the DTSTART property in iCalendar.
                        If the event has a different end time zone to start time zone, this should be
                        added as a JSCalendar <spanx style="emph">location</spanx> with just a
                        <spanx style="emph">timeZone</spanx> property and <spanx style="verb">rel="end"</spanx>.
                    </c>

                    <c>duration</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the DURATION or DSTART+DTEND properties in iCalendar.
                      </c>
                </texttable>

            </section>

            <section anchor="translate-jstask" title="JSTask">
                <t>
                    The iCalendar counterpart to <spanx style="emph">JSTask</spanx> is the VTODO component type
                    <xref target="RFC5545"/>. A VTODO component that is a direct child of a VCALENDAR component is
                    equivalent to a standalone JSTask. A VTODO component within a master
                    VTODO maps to the entries of
                    the JSTask <spanx style="emph">recurrenceOverrides</spanx> property.
                </t>

                <texttable anchor="translate-jstask-table" title="Translation between JSTask and iCalendar">
                <ttcol align='left'>Property</ttcol>
                <ttcol align='left'>iCalendar counterpart</ttcol>

                    <c>isAllDay</c>
                    <c>
                        True, if the type of the DTSTART property in iCalendar is DATE.
                    </c>

                    <c>due</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the DUE and DTSTART+DURATION properties in iCalendar. When mapping iCalendar
                        VTODOs with DTSTART+DURATION, the due date is the result of adding DURATION to DTSTART in the
                        DTSTART time zone.
                    </c>

                    <c>start</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the DTSTART property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>timeZone</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the TZID part of the DTSTART/DUE properties in iCalendar.
                        If the task has a different end time zone to start or due time zone, this should be
                        added as a JSCalendar <spanx style="emph">location</spanx> with just a
                        <spanx style="emph">timeZone</spanx> property and <spanx style="verb">rel="end"</spanx>.
                    </c>

                    <c>estimatedDuration</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the ESTIMATED-DURATION iCalendar
                        property in the RFC draft <xref target="draft-apthorp-ical-tasks"/>.
                    </c>

                    <c>statusUpdatedAt</c>
                    <c>
                      Maps to the COMPLETED iCalendar property. The JSTask status property
                      MUST have value <spanx style="verb">completed</spanx>.
                    </c>

                    <c>progress</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the PARTSTAT and COMPLETED properties in iCalendar, including the
                        definitions in the RFC draft <xref target="draft-apthorp-ical-tasks"/>.
                    </c>

                    <c>status</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the STATUS property in iCalendar, including the
                        definitions in the RFC draft <xref target="draft-apthorp-ical-tasks"/>.
                    </c>

                </texttable>
            </section>

            <section title="JSGroup">
                <t>
                    A JSGroup converts to a iCalendar VCALENDAR containing VEVENT or VTODO components.
                </t>

                <texttable anchor="translate-jsgroup-table" title="Translation between JSGroup and iCalendar">
                    <ttcol align='left'>Property</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='left'>iCalendar counterpart</ttcol>

                    <c>entries</c>
                    <c>
                        The VEVENT and VTODO components within a top-level VCALENDAR component.
                    </c>

                    <c>source</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the SOURCE property in iCalendar.
                    </c>
                </texttable>
            </section>

            <section title="Common properties">
              <texttable anchor="translate-commonprops-table" title="Translation between JSCalendar and iCalendar">

                <ttcol align='left'>Property</ttcol>
                <ttcol align='left'>iCalendar counterpart</ttcol>

                    <c>alerts</c>
                    <c>
                        An <spanx style="emph">Alert</spanx> corresponds to the VALARM component in iCalendar, where
                        the <spanx style="emph">action</spanx> is determined by the iCalendar ACTION property value
                        (e.g., both <spanx style="verb">DISPLAY</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">AUDIO</spanx> actions
                        map to a JSCalendar <spanx style="emph">display</spanx> action, and similarly for
                        <spanx style="verb">EMAIL</spanx>).
                        The OffsetTrigger <spanx style="emph">relativeTo</spanx> and <spanx style="emph">offset</spanx>
                        properties corresponds to the iCalendar TRIGGER property.
                    </c>

                    <c>categories</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the CONCEPT property in iCalendar,
                        see in the RFC draft <xref target="draft-ietf-calext-ical-relations"/>.
                    </c>

                    <c>color</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the COLOR property in iCalendar, as specified in <xref target="RFC7986"/>.
                    </c>

                    <c>created</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the CREATED property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>description</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the DESCRIPTION property and its ALTREP parameters in iCalendar.
                    </c>
                    <c>descriptionContentType</c>
                    <c>
                      Implementation-specific.
                    </c>

                    <c>freeBusyStatus</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the TRANSP property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>keywords</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the CATEGORIES property in iCalendar, as specified in <xref target="RFC7986"/>.
                    </c>

                    <c>links</c>
                    <c>
                      Use the ATTACH (<xref target="RFC5545"/>), URL or IMAGE (<xref target="RFC7986"/>)
                      property values of URI value type as the Link <spanx style="emph">href</spanx>.
                      The Link <spanx style="emph">type</spanx> property
                      corresponds to the FMTTYPE parameter, the <spanx style="emph">size</spanx>
                      property to the SIZE parameter.
                      Mapping all other properties is implementation-specific.
                    </c>

                    <c>locale</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the LANGUAGE parameter in iCalendar, which is added to individual properties.
                        When converting from iCalendar, one language must be picked as the main locale for the
                        object, and all properties in other languages moved to the localizations JSEvent property.
                    </c>

                    <c>localizations</c>
                    <c>
                        Implementation-specific.
                    </c>

                    <c>locations</c>
                    <c>
                        See <xref target="translate-locations-participants"/>.
                    </c>

                    <c>method</c>
                    <c>
                      Corresponds to the METHOD property of the embedding VCALENDAR in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>participants</c>
                    <c>
                        See <xref target="translate-locations-participants"/>.
                    </c>

                    <c>priority</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the PRIORITY property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>privacy</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the CLASS property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>prodId</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the PRODID property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>recurrenceOverrides</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the RDATE and EXDATE properties in iCalendar, plus VEVENT (for JSEvent) or
                        VTODO (for JSTask) instances with a recurrence-id.
                    </c>

                    <c>recurrenceRule</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the RRULE property in iCalendar. For all-day calendar objects,
                        convert the <spanx style="emph">until</spanx> property value to an iCalendar
                        DATE (effectively removing the time component). To convert a DATE-typed UNTIL
                        from iCalendar, set the time components of the LocalDate value to
                        <spanx style="verb">23:59:59</spanx>. If the iCalendar UNTIL value is a
                        UTC date time, convert to the local time in the calendar object time zone.
                    </c>

                    <c>relatedTo</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the RELATED-TO property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>replyTo</c>
                    <c>
                      An iCalendar ORGANIZER with a mailto: URI mapped to the
                        <spanx style="verb">imip</spanx> method, or any other
                        URI mapped to the <spanx style="verb">other</spanx>
                        method. Mapping multiple methods is implementation-specific.
                    </c>

                    <c>sequence</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the SEQUENCE property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>status</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the STATUS property in iCalendar (converted to lower-case).
                    </c>

                    <c>title</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the SUMMARY property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>uid</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the UID property in iCalendar.
                    </c>

                    <c>updated</c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the DTSTAMP and LAST-MODIFIED properties in iCalendar. (These are only
                        different in the iTIP case, and the difference is not actually useful.)
                    </c>
                </texttable>
            </section>

            <section anchor="translate-locations-participants" title="Locations and participants">
                <t>
                    Both JSCalendar participants and locations have counterparts in iCalendar
                    but provide richer representation.
                    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                    The following table outlines translation of JSCalendar participants. Where
                    iCalendar has distinct properties for ORGANIZER and ATTENDEE, these are merged
                    in JSCalendar into the Participant object type.
                </t>
                <texttable anchor="translate-participants-table"
                  title="Translation of Participant between JSCalendar and iCalendar">
                    <ttcol align='left'>Property</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='left'>iCalendar counterpart</ttcol>
                    <c>delegatedFrom</c>
                    <c>
                        the DELEGATED-FROM parameter
                    </c>

                    <c> delegatedTo</c>
                    <c>
                      the DELEGATED-TO parameter
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        expectReply
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        the RSVP parameter
                    </c>

                    <c>email</c>
                    <c>
                        The value of the EMAIL parameter of the ORGANIZER or ATTENDEE property, if
                        defined. Otherwise the property value, if it is a mailto: URI.
                    </c>
                    <c>sendTo</c>
                    <c>
                        An iCalendar ATTENDEE with a mailto: URI mapped to the
                        <spanx style="verb">imip</spanx> method, or any other
                        URI mapped to the <spanx style="verb">other</spanx>
                        method. Mapping multiple methods is implementation-specific.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        kind
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        the CUTYPE parameter
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        linkIds
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        Implementation-specific.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        locationId
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        Implementation-specific. When mapping from iCalendar to JSCalendar this
                        may be the JSCalendar identifier of a CONFERENCE property that has the
                        MODERATOR feature defined in its FEATURE parameter values. If multiple
                        such CONFERENCE properties are defined in iCalendar, then the one with the
                        most interactive features is chosen.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        memberOf
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        the MEMBER parameter
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        name
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        the CN parameter
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        attendance
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      Maps to the standard iCalendar ROLE parameter values REQ-PARTICIPANT, OPT-PARTICIPANT and
                      NON-PARTICIPANT.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        roles
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      The <spanx style="verb">chair</spanx> role maps to the standard iCalendar ROLE
                      parameter value <spanx style="verb">chair</spanx>, with an implicit participant
                      of value <spanx style="verb">required</spanx>. The mapping of non-required chairs
                      and other roles is implementation-specific, but using <spanx style="verb">x-name</spanx>
                      parameter values is recommended.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        participationStatus
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        the PARTSTAT parameter
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        scheduleSequence
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        the SEQUENCE property of the participant's latest iMIP message
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        scheduleUpdated
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        the DTSTAMP property of the participant's latest iMIP message
                    </c>
                </texttable>
                <t>
                    The iCalendar counterpart for JSCalendar Location objects is the iCalendar
                    <xref target="RFC5545"/> LOCATION property, or implementation-specific.
                  </t>
                <texttable anchor="translate-locations-table"
                  title="Translation of Location between JSCalendar and iCalendar">
                    <ttcol align='left'>Property</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='left'>iCalendar counterpart</ttcol>
                    <c>
                       name
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      Corresponds to the LOCATION property value.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                       description
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      Implementation-specific.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                       rel
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      Implementation-specific.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                       timeZone
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      Implementation-specific.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                       coordinates
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      Implementation-specific. Consider using a GEO iCalendar property, along with one LOCATION.
                      </c>
                    <c>
                       uri
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      Corresponds to the LOCATION ALTREP parameter.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      linkIds
                    </c>
                    <c>
                      Implementation-specific.
                    </c>
                </texttable>
                <t>
                    The iCalendar counterpart for JSCalendar VirtualLocation objects is the iCalendar
                    <xref target="RFC7986"/> CONFERENCE property, or implementation-specific.
                </t>
                <texttable anchor="translate-virtualLocations-table"
                  title="Translation of VirtualLocation between JSCalendar and iCalendar">
                    <ttcol align='left'>Property</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='left'>iCalendar counterpart</ttcol>
                    <c>
                        name
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the CONFERENCE LABEL parameter.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        description
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        Implementation-specific.
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        uri
                    </c>
                    <c>
                        Corresponds to the CONFERENCE property value.
                    </c>
                </texttable>
            </section>

            <section title="iCalendarProperties">
                <t>
                    When converting from JSCalendar to iCalendar, apply first
                    the iCalendar properties in a stub iCalendar component,
                    then overwrite all properties that have a known conversion
                    from JSCalendar to iCalendar. When converting from iCalendar,
                    only include properties that were not converted to any
                    JSCalendar property or object.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                The same security considerations as for <xref target="draft-ietf-calext-jscalendar"/> apply.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
                None.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>
                The authors would like to thank the members of CalConnect for their valuable contributions. This
                specification originated from the work of the API technical committee of CalConnect, the Calendaring and
                Scheduling Consortium.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2392.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4122.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4791.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5545.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5546.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5870.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6047.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6838.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6901.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7265.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7493.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7529.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7808.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7986.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8259.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8288.xml"?>
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">
            <reference anchor="draft-ietf-calext-jscalendar"
                target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-calext-jscalendar">
                <front>
                    <title>Task Extensions to iCalendar</title>
                    <author/>
                    <date/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="draft-apthorp-ical-tasks"
                       target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-apthorp-ical-tasks">
                <front>
                    <title>Task Extensions to iCalendar</title>
                    <author/>
                    <date/>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="draft-ietf-calext-ical-relations"
                       target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-calext-ical-relations">
                <front>
                    <title>Support for iCalendar Relationships</title>
                    <author/>
                    <date/>
                </front>
              </reference>
            <reference anchor="MIME"
              target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/media-types.xhtml">
                <front>
                    <title>IANA Media Types</title>
                    <author/>
                    <date/>
                </front>
            </reference>

        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
